<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>3DStreet Blog</title>
        <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog</link>
        <description>3DStreet Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Announcing 3DStreet Geospatial Pro Early Access]]></title>
            <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro</link>
            <guid>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[We’re thrilled to introduce 3DStreet Geospatial Pro, our latest product update that brings you revolutionary 3D map integrations, drag-and-drop 3D model placement, augmented reality features, and much more!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We’re thrilled to announce the early access launch of 3DStreet Geospatial Pro introducing groundbreaking 3D map integrations, drag-and-drop 3D model placement, augmented reality features, and more.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/geospatial-pro-64e43a4a7664bb184920de93ba52436f.jpg" width="1259" height="1274" class="img_ev3q"><br><i>
<strong>Community advocate Andrew Seigner used 3DStreet Geospatial Pro to propose a few alternative treatments for a Hayes Street Promenade in San Francisco.</strong></i></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-3dstreet-geospatial-pro">Why 3DStreet Geospatial Pro?<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro#why-3dstreet-geospatial-pro" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why 3DStreet Geospatial Pro?" title="Direct link to Why 3DStreet Geospatial Pro?">​</a></h2>
<p>Since launching 3DStreet in 2017, our mission has been to empower everyone to reimagine public spaces. After the successful release of 3DStreet Cloud, we've listened to feedback from a diverse community of users—ranging from transportation engineers to community advocates. The common request? Tools to provide geographical context for street designs.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="design-scenes-with-integrated-2d--3d-maps">Design Scenes with Integrated 2D &amp; 3D Maps<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro#design-scenes-with-integrated-2d--3d-maps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Design Scenes with Integrated 2D &amp; 3D Maps" title="Direct link to Design Scenes with Integrated 2D &amp; 3D Maps">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/mapbox-sketchfab-gltf-placement-da1f5b42123d21ba14f72a8a8dd10b72.jpg" width="1280" height="962" class="img_ev3q"><br><i>
<strong>A proposed street plaza design from landscape architecture firm Terrain Studio aligned with real-world geometry using 3DStreet Geospatial Pro.</strong></i></p>
<p>3DStreet Geospatial Pro makes it easy to integrate detailed 2D and 3D maps from various providers. Use Mapbox's 2D Satellite layer for fine detail and Google’s 3D Map layer for lifelike context. Each scene can now be linked to specific geographical coordinates, unlocking advanced geospatial features like QR-code based Augmented Reality.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/scenelocation-settings-1ff7ecdeafeff878878da7ce86f148b5.jpg" width="753" height="663" class="img_ev3q"><br><i>
<strong>Setting a Scene Location is a simple as searching for a place with Google Maps.</strong></i></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="add-objects-and-layers-easily">Add Objects and Layers Easily<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro#add-objects-and-layers-easily" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Add Objects and Layers Easily" title="Direct link to Add Objects and Layers Easily">​</a></h2>
<p>Our rich library of custom-designed 3D objects is now more accessible with a new Add Entity panel. Browse and add everything from pedestrians and vehicles to buildings and street props to your scene with just a few clicks.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/add-new-entity-panel-880a80409af05cd57c411c7cb9985f1f.jpg" width="632" height="386" class="img_ev3q"><br><i>
<strong>Adding new layers and 3D models to your scene is as easy as scrolling and clicking.</strong></i></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="combine-advanced-street-geometry-from-multiple-providers">Combine Advanced Street Geometry from Multiple Providers<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro#combine-advanced-street-geometry-from-multiple-providers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Combine Advanced Street Geometry from Multiple Providers" title="Direct link to Combine Advanced Street Geometry from Multiple Providers">​</a></h2>
<p>We now support Street Layers from multiple street design platforms including Streetmix, StreetPlan, and a new intersection component. Create your own custom paths by importing svg files from vector graphic editing software such as Figma. Coming soon, import custom 3D scans in Gaussian splat format created with applications such as LumaAI and Polycam.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/mission-bay-traffic-circle-rev4-298a0ace3bdfeb768fe7c0d4535b4a0e.jpg" width="1080" height="611" class="img_ev3q"><br><i>
<strong>Using a custom SVG paths created in Figma and imported into 3DStreet is a quick way to prototype a mode-separated traffic circle.</strong></i></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="optimized-gltf-export-for-augmented-reality">Optimized glTF Export for Augmented Reality<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro#optimized-gltf-export-for-augmented-reality" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Optimized glTF Export for Augmented Reality" title="Direct link to Optimized glTF Export for Augmented Reality">​</a></h2>
<p>We're simplifying AR visualization with an “Optimized for AR” export option. This feature automatically prepares your 3DStreet scenes for use in AR apps like <a href="https://www.adobe.com/products/aero.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Aero</a> and <a href="https://incitu.us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">inCitu</a>, eliminating the need for additional 3D model editing.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SszAFmtmVC4?si=anecoEum53Y9C4sF" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin"></iframe>
<br>
<i><strong>A first-person recording of street design changes created in 3DStreet composited with real-world imagery using Adobe Aero.</strong></i>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="upcoming-ar-features">Upcoming AR Features<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro#upcoming-ar-features" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Upcoming AR Features" title="Direct link to Upcoming AR Features">​</a></h2>
<p>We are also developing a 3DStreet mobile WebAR app providing Augmented Reality experiences using QR codes for localization.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/ar-screencaps-e46383f26b19e9bc1813fe038e6409a6.jpg" width="1142" height="1024" class="img_ev3q"><br><i>
<strong>Augmented Reality visualization allows realtime compositing of your proposed design placed in the real-world.</strong></i></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="pricing-and-availability">Pricing and Availability<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro#pricing-and-availability" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Pricing and Availability" title="Direct link to Pricing and Availability">​</a></h2>
<p>3DStreet Geospatial Pro is available as a subscription for $49/month, with discounts for annual payments. While most existing free features will remain available, advanced features like geospatial tools, smart layers, and AR export will only be available as part of the Pro plan.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="early-access">Early Access<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/06/14/announcing-3dstreet-geospatial-pro#early-access" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Early Access" title="Direct link to Early Access">​</a></h2>
<p>Ready to transform your projects with cutting-edge geospatial features?</p>
<p><a href="https://us6.list-manage.com/contact-form?u=01ce9902276fa6ad96be57ac6&amp;form_id=3f024b297f2177befa87b5ca5e9d45cc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Contact us to get Early Access to 3DStreet Geospatial Pro</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>product update</category>
            <category>3dtiles</category>
            <category>google maps</category>
            <category>geospatial</category>
            <category>ar</category>
            <category>mapbox</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Community-Led Design of Safe “School Streets” for Mission Bay Elementary School]]></title>
            <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school</link>
            <guid>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[In San Francisco's Mission Bay neighborhood, community leaders used 3DStreet's rapid prototyping service to create a 3D digital twin of proposed street safety improvements around a new elementary school, helping them effectively advocate for the project with city officials and stakeholders.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In San Francisco's Mission Bay neighborhood, community leaders used 3DStreet's rapid prototyping service to create a 3D digital twin of proposed street safety improvements around a new elementary school, helping them effectively advocate for the project with city officials and stakeholders.</p>
<img-comparison-slider><img slot="first" width="100%" src="https://cdn.glitch.global/185d7b67-1046-4065-8ddc-d1850cd3d096/mission-bay-1.jpg?v=1711755971050"><img slot="second" width="100%" src="https://cdn.glitch.global/185d7b67-1046-4065-8ddc-d1850cd3d096/mission-bay-2.jpg?v=1711755969977"></img-comparison-slider>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-neighborhood-no-school">New Neighborhood, No School<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school#new-neighborhood-no-school" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New Neighborhood, No School" title="Direct link to New Neighborhood, No School">​</a></h2>
<p>San Francisco’s Mission Bay neighborhood is one of the fastest growing areas in the City. From 2010-2020, it doubled its population by hosting many of SF’s new residential building projects. [1] [2] Mission Bay is also host to well-known firms like OpenAI, Uber, and UCSF, not to mention world-class entertainment facilities like the newly built Chase Center, home of the Golden State Warriors.</p>
<p>But there’s one glaring omission in Mission Bay – there are no schools. “There currently are no elementary, middle, or high schools, public or private, in the Mission Bay area,” said Matt Haney in 2017, then President of the Board for SF public schools. “This is unacceptable. This is a community that urgently deserves and needs a school.” [3]</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/mission-bay-es-empty-site-03bc0f97c4b0e92642f35bcb6a03dc23.jpg" width="1268" height="667" class="img_ev3q"><br><i>
The future site for an elementary school building in Mission Bay, San Francisco is currently a parking lot sitting on top of rocky fill covering what was once part of an actual bay and tidal wetlands. [4]</i></p>
<p>25 years after being proposed in a 1998 Mission Bay redevelopment plan, construction on a school in the neighborhood has finally begun! The $90 million Mission Bay Elementary School project is expected to be completed in time to open for the school year starting August 2025. [5]</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-neighborhood-old-school-transportation">New Neighborhood, Old School Transportation<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school#new-neighborhood-old-school-transportation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New Neighborhood, Old School Transportation" title="Direct link to New Neighborhood, Old School Transportation">​</a></h2>
<p>Despite its recent development, Mission Bay was designed with no protected active transportation facilities aside from bayside trails. Many of its streets consist of 3 lanes dedicated to motor vehicles in each direction (2 travel, 1 parking) with no separated bike lanes, few painted ones, and copious sharrows. While effective in accommodating egress vehicle traffic after Warriors and Giants games, existing street space does not promote active mobility for neighborhood residents and school children.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/mission-bay-es-nearby-intersection-large-roads-4b445b9094703687b9354970549c72ce.jpg" width="1260" height="677" class="img_ev3q"><br>
<i>Owens Street meets Nelson Rising Lanes in Mission Bay, San Francisco. The parcel northeast of the intersection (currently occupied by a parking lot) is the future site of the proposed SFUSD Mission Bay Elementary School.</i></p>
<p>Local community members are excited about the prospect of improving street conditions to encourage active walking, biking and mobility for students living in the neighborhood.</p>
<p>“Mission Bay is a densely populated, flat neighborhood, so it just makes sense to provide active mobility options for students going to school. But we are faced with a built environment that prioritizes the car and makes walking and cycling a scary proposition for parents,” said Peter Belden, a community activist and San Francisco’s 2024 Bike Champion of the Year.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="community-groups-envision-a-better-future-change">Community Groups Envision a Better Future Change<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school#community-groups-envision-a-better-future-change" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Community Groups Envision a Better Future Change" title="Direct link to Community Groups Envision a Better Future Change">​</a></h2>
<p>However, community leaders were disappointed with the limited resources dedicated to improving street safety ahead of construction of the new school. While the City committed to fund a study [6] to identify problem areas and suggest possible designs for a few trouble spots, it fell short of community expectations by not delivering a comprehensive, neighborhood-wide plan for safe walking and biking access to the school.</p>
<p>The community took it upon themselves to create their own designs. “We started by rethinking the traffic circle neighboring the new school and originally designed to accommodate peak vehicle flows after ball games. With a school going in next door, we wanted to re-imagine it as best-in-class infrastructure that separates modes, providing a safety buffer for vulnerable road users while allowing residents to access nature and planned affordable housing without the need for a car,” explained Nik Kaestner, the former Director of Sustainability at SFUSD.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/mission-bay-es-traffic-circle-hand-drawings-1fcdf5d5c87d8d28c324de1b1e8944a6.jpeg" width="1024" height="799" class="img_ev3q"><br>
A hand-drawn sketch by Nik Kaestner to illustrate core concepts of a proposed project to add separated cycling facilities to an existing traffic circle at the intersection of Mission Bay Drive and Owens St.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="from-idea-to-prototype-with-3dstreet-rapid-prototyping-service">From Idea to Prototype with 3DStreet Rapid Prototyping Service<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school#from-idea-to-prototype-with-3dstreet-rapid-prototyping-service" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to From Idea to Prototype with 3DStreet Rapid Prototyping Service" title="Direct link to From Idea to Prototype with 3DStreet Rapid Prototyping Service">​</a></h2>
<p>“We were inspired by ‘Dutch-style’ roundabouts [7] with full separation continuing through the intersection, not only along approaching streets,” continued Kaestner. “But we were limited in our ability to convert our vision from hand-drawn sketches into a practical prototype that would excite fellow advocates and be taken seriously by City staff.”</p>
<mux-player player-software-name="mux-player-react" player-software-version="2.5.0" stream-type="on-demand" primary-color="#FFFFFF" secondary-color="#000000" accent-color="#653CB0" autoplay="muted" loop=""></mux-player>
<br>
<i>Animation generated by 3DStreet showing the evolution from existing conditions of a mixed-mode traffic circle to a mode-separated traffic circle.</i>
<p>Community leaders turned to 3DStreet for help in converting the sketch into a 3D prototype that can be used  in advocacy and planning conversations with City staff and elected officials.</p>
<p>This simplified “digital twin” encompasses a virtual representation of both the existing conditions and proposed future changes. Hosting on 3DStreet Cloud allowed the team to create visuals for specific use-cases on demand and share these with others to further remix.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="adding-context-with-real-world-elements">Adding Context with Real World Elements<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school#adding-context-with-real-world-elements" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Adding Context with Real World Elements" title="Direct link to Adding Context with Real World Elements">​</a></h2>
<p>To provide visual context for stakeholders reviewing proposed changes, community leaders added real-world surface scan maps and a 3D model of the proposed elementary school using 3DStreet’s Geospatial Pro features.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/mission-bay-traffic-circle-rev4-298a0ace3bdfeb768fe7c0d4535b4a0e.jpg" width="1080" height="611" class="img_ev3q"><br>
<i>Adding the Mapbox satellite map ground layer along with a low fidelity 3D model of the school building helped ground the visualization in the present-day context.</i></p>
<p>Leveraging multiple camera perspectives, especially simulating a first-person view, was especially helpful to share critical design attributes with stakeholders.</p>
<p>“As our neighborhood develops a vision for how we will welcome the Mission Bay school, this tool is a great gift to outreach and engagement with both elected officials and agency staff.The multi viewpoint visualization, especially the first-person animation of traffic circle usage at a child’s height and the before/after slider bar feature clearly convey what is possible.” said Sarah Bertram, a local community member advocating on behalf of neighboring residents.</p>
<mux-player player-software-name="mux-player-react" player-software-version="2.5.0" stream-type="on-demand" primary-color="#FFFFFF" secondary-color="#000000" accent-color="#653CB0" autoplay="muted" loop=""></mux-player>
<br>
<i>Animation generated by 3DStreet showing the first-person animation of traffic circle usage at a child's height.</i>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="is-it-feasible-from-3d-prototypes-to-civil-drawings">Is it Feasible? From 3D Prototypes to Civil Drawings<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school#is-it-feasible-from-3d-prototypes-to-civil-drawings" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Is it Feasible? From 3D Prototypes to Civil Drawings" title="Direct link to Is it Feasible? From 3D Prototypes to Civil Drawings">​</a></h2>
<p>This project is just starting. The school has broken ground with more than a year of construction remaining. While the prototypes of safer school streets are winning people’s hearts, the constraints of budget and technical feasibility are the next issues to tackle for community and City stakeholders.</p>
<p>Fortunately, 3DStreet gives stakeholders a head start as they consider more detailed civil plans. “3DStreet’s ability to export to other popular file formats allowed us to jumpstart the manual process of preparing baseline conditions so that our valuable engineer time can be better spent on project-specific requirements,” said Jorge Romero-Lozano, a civil engineer and executive director of GreeningProjects.org, who also consulted on the project.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="make-your-next-community-led-project-a-success">Make Your Next Community-Led Project a Success<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school#make-your-next-community-led-project-a-success" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Make Your Next Community-Led Project a Success" title="Direct link to Make Your Next Community-Led Project a Success">​</a></h2>
<p>Let us help you with your next community-led improvement project. Our team is available to provide assistance as you navigate the community-led development process, from ideation to prototyping, stakeholder communication, and community outreach empowered by next generation technology. <a href="https://3dstreet.org/docs/services/">Learn more about our Rapid Prototype Service to quickly move your project to the next stage.</a></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="references">References<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/05/24/community-led-design-of-safe-school-streets-for-mission-bay-elementary-school#references" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to References" title="Direct link to References">​</a></h3>
<p>[1] <a href="https://www.potreroview.net/mission-bays-population-almost-doubled-in-last-decade/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.potreroview.net/mission-bays-population-almost-doubled-in-last-decade/</a></p>
<p>[2] <a href="https://www.sf.gov/news/city-celebrates-opening-and-dedication-affordable-housing-mission-bay" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.sf.gov/news/city-celebrates-opening-and-dedication-affordable-housing-mission-bay</a></p>
<p>[3] <a href="https://www.potreroview.net/new-mission-bay-public-school-to-be-launched-within-five-years/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.potreroview.net/new-mission-bay-public-school-to-be-launched-within-five-years/</a></p>
<p>[4] <a href="https://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=Filling_The_Bay_Along_San_Francisco%E2%80%99s_Southern_Waterfront" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.foundsf.org/index.php?title=Filling_The_Bay_Along_San_Francisco%E2%80%99s_Southern_Waterfront</a></p>
<p>[4] <a href="https://www.sfusd.edu/about-sfusd/sfusd-news/press-releases/2022-10-27-construction-set-begin-new-sfusd-school-mission-bay" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.sfusd.edu/about-sfusd/sfusd-news/press-releases/2022-10-27-construction-set-begin-new-sfusd-school-mission-bay</a></p>
<p>[5] <a href="https://sfyimby.com/2023/02/sitework-underway-for-mission-bay-school-in-san-francisco.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://sfyimby.com/2023/02/sitework-underway-for-mission-bay-school-in-san-francisco.html</a></p>
<p>[6] <a href="https://www.sfcta.org/mission-bay-school" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.sfcta.org/mission-bay-school</a> Plan provided by the SFCTA, a SF County agency which is separate from the SF Municipal Transportation Agency. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco_County_Transportation_Authority" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco_County_Transportation_Authority</a></p>
<p>[7] <a href="https://bicycledutch.wordpress.com/2015/10/13/explaining-the-dutch-roundabout-abroad/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://bicycledutch.wordpress.com/2015/10/13/explaining-the-dutch-roundabout-abroad/</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>safe streets</category>
            <category>school streets</category>
            <category>intersection</category>
            <category>community-led planning</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Community-led planning trends presented at the Caltrans Equity Advisory Committee]]></title>
            <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/04/22/community-led-planning-trends-at-caltrans-equity-advisory-committee</link>
            <guid>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/04/22/community-led-planning-trends-at-caltrans-equity-advisory-committee</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[At the recent Caltrans EAC meeting a host of agency professionals, community leaders and technology experts like 3DStreet’s own Kieran Farr shared expertise on the global trend of community-led planning.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At the recent Caltrans EAC meeting a host of agency professionals, community leaders and technology experts like 3DStreet’s own Kieran Farr shared expertise on the global trend of community-led planning and the current blockers preventing local stakeholders from engaging with local transportation agencies. Below is a summarization of the presentation to share our learnings from practitioners around the world experimenting with community-led design.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="community-led-planning-as-global-trend">Community-Led Planning as Global Trend<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/04/22/community-led-planning-trends-at-caltrans-equity-advisory-committee#community-led-planning-as-global-trend" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Community-Led Planning as Global Trend" title="Direct link to Community-Led Planning as Global Trend">​</a></h2>
<p>Over the past 6 months I've met hundreds of folks across the transportation and planning industry – from city planners and city and state transportation officials to local community activists, NGOs, private engineering consultants and many more.</p>
<p>Hundreds of meetings later, a clear trend has emerged from these conversations: The rising force of "Community-led Planning" – empowering local community members to envision and advocate for changes to their streets and public spaces. However, there are significant challenges preventing this from becoming mainstream practice.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-challenge---negative-trust-spiral">The Challenge - Negative Trust Spiral<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/04/22/community-led-planning-trends-at-caltrans-equity-advisory-committee#the-challenge---negative-trust-spiral" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Challenge - Negative Trust Spiral" title="Direct link to The Challenge - Negative Trust Spiral">​</a></h2>
<p>The core issue, as articulated by practitioners worldwide, is that it's very difficult for most people to imagine changes to their streets. This leads to a negative feedback loop:</p>
<ul>
<li>Projects face pushback from the community because they don't understand the proposed changes</li>
<li>This results in delays, watered-down designs, or even outright cancellations</li>
<li>Trust erodes between the agency and community</li>
</ul>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/slide-challenge-negative-trust-spiral-current-conditions-street-planning-projects-1dc5cebcd64eca88e345c10e93a7a890.jpg" width="960" height="540" class="img_ev3q">
<strong>Community engagement is often treated as a point-in-time exercise rather than a continuous process.</strong></p>
<p>Forward-thinking communities are trying to change this by making community feedback an integral, ongoing part of the planning process. Crucially, project ideas originate from the community itself, which then collaborates with the appropriate agency to refine the design to serve local needs.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="addressing-agencycommunity-asymmetry">Addressing Agency/Community Asymmetry<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/04/22/community-led-planning-trends-at-caltrans-equity-advisory-committee#addressing-agencycommunity-asymmetry" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Addressing Agency/Community Asymmetry" title="Direct link to Addressing Agency/Community Asymmetry">​</a></h2>
<p>Underlying this dynamic is a major knowledge asymmetry between transportation professionals and the general public when it comes to street design.</p>
<p>To enable meaningful community participation we need to level the playing field – to lift up community members from out of the informational asymmetry crevasse. One way to do this is through a simple, shared visual language to understand the geospatial relationships and design constraints of their streets. This is the key problem we're working to solve at 3DStreet, along with other industry partners <a href="https://about.streetmix.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Streetmix.net</a>, <a href="https://www.incitu.us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">inCitu</a>, <a href="https://streetplan.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">StreetPlan.net</a>, and the <a href="https://hackmd.io/legG6QzVREKTsiTSxUS2zA?view" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OSM Pedestrian Working Group</a>.</p>
<p>This emerging ecosystem of no/low cost tools allow anyone to quickly prototype street designs, transforming 2D diagrams into interactive 3D models. Early case studies show the power of this approach:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ycNIaqczyv0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">In Manchester, CA, the city engineer used 3DStreet to clearly communicate parking tradeoffs for a Main Street redesign, a top concern for local businesses</a></li>
<li><a href="https://studio.youtube.com/video/m393-ZNeU68/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NGOs like Transport Oakland are training their members to create compelling visuals for advocacy using these tools on group workshop calls</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#reaction-and-productization-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">At a street fair in San Francisco, we enabled attendees to interactively place street furniture, plantings and amenities using just their smartphones to imagine a green "streets to parks" conversion</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Historically, 3D modeling, urban planning and civil engineering required expensive proprietary software. But with the consumerization of augmented reality and open-source tools like 3DStreet combined with widely-deployed WebXR and geospatial standards, these capabilities are now accessible to all. While much work remains to make them truly user-friendly, the potential to revolutionize community engagement is tremendous.</p>
<p>By equipping residents with the tools to express their vision, while educating them about real-world constraints, we can build trust, understanding and consensus between communities and transportation agencies. This is the promise of community-led planning – and it's a future we're excited to build together.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>policy</category>
            <category>urban planning</category>
            <category>community-led planning</category>
            <category>community</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Exploring New Geospatial and Augmented Reality Features for 3DStreet]]></title>
            <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research</link>
            <guid>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A developer update blog post on R&D during the first few months of 2024.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>"Geospatial" is the uniting theme for the many feature requests we get from 3DStreet's growing user base. Users&nbsp;can already place custom street scenes, so it's natural to understand why geospatial features like 3D Google Map Tiles or Augmented Reality visualization keep coming up in conversations with users when we <a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero">explore common repeatable workflows for visualizing safer infrastructure</a>.</p>
<p>To kick off 2024 we've been doing some experiments to see how these technologies could be applied to public streets and spatial design.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/3d-tiles-3dstreet-aa3921b202e721e8fb32544a6f6f4f6d.jpeg" width="1024" height="886" class="img_ev3q">
<strong>Proof of concept 3D Tiles and 3DStreet scene combined.</strong></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="google-maps-3d-tiles">Google Maps 3D Tiles<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#google-maps-3d-tiles" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Google Maps 3D Tiles" title="Direct link to Google Maps 3D Tiles">​</a></h2>
<p>We updated the New York Times R&amp;D team's <a href="https://github.com/nytimes/aframe-loader-3dtiles-component?tab=readme-ov-file#using-google-3d-tiles-api" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub repository for the OGC 3D Tiles A-Frame VR Component</a> to support loading 3D maps from Google Maps 3D Tiles. (Thanks Avner for doing the hard three.js work to make this happen.)</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-is-this-important">Why is this important?<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#why-is-this-important" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why is this important?" title="Direct link to Why is this important?">​</a></h3>
<p>When presenting street improvements projects, leveraging the existing environment provides instantaneous context and understanding for stakeholders of all ages and abilities. Even low fidelity representations of the surrounding environment helps viewers recognize a project's location and orientation.</p>
<p>This experiment is a first step to adding 3D maps as a new feature to 3DStreet Editor.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="video-demo">Video Demo<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#video-demo" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Video Demo" title="Direct link to Video Demo">​</a></h3>
<p>This video is a demo of what it could look like to localize your 3DStreet scene with 3D map tiles near Market and Van Ness Streets in San Francisco.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JRWd8P4QwTs?si=lAx7vGRB_rrVIqf6" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin"></iframe>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reaction-and-productization">Reaction and productization<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#reaction-and-productization" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Reaction and productization" title="Direct link to Reaction and productization">​</a></h3>
<p>This demo resonated well with users -- <a href="https://twitter.com/3dstreetapp/status/1768310079307272423" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our first tweet sharing the concept</a> was retweeted 11 times and liked more than 50 times on Twitter and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/3dstreet_threejs-activity-7174079008819560449-kzqw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">attracted engaging comments on LinkedIn</a>.</p>
<p>Users would like 3D Map Tiles productized as a built-in feature of 3DStreet, but unfortunately the Google 3D Tiles API is significantly more expensive than traditional 2D map tiles starting at <a href="https://github.com/nytimes/aframe-loader-3dtiles-component?tab=readme-ov-file#using-google-3d-tiles-api" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">$6 per 1000 unique user sessions</a>. In order to offer this feature we will need to come up with a paid subscription plan option to cover the costs of Google Maps 3D Tiles access.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bollard-buddy-ar---mobile-app-for-manual-geolocation-and-object-placement">Bollard Buddy AR - mobile app for manual geolocation and object placement<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#bollard-buddy-ar---mobile-app-for-manual-geolocation-and-object-placement" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bollard Buddy AR - mobile app for manual geolocation and object placement" title="Direct link to Bollard Buddy AR - mobile app for manual geolocation and object placement">​</a></h2>
<p>The recent <a href="https://dreamxr.co/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">DreamXR hackathon</a> in San Francisco was the perfect environment to work alongside other XR developers for inspiration to finish a new app in 48 hours. We created BOLLARD BUDDY AR -- an app that lets you place traffic control devices anywhere using augmented reality!</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="video-demo-1">Video Demo<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#video-demo-1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Video Demo" title="Direct link to Video Demo">​</a></h3>
<p>It's easiest to show with a video:</p>
<iframe width="315" height="560" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mP32oAlz8iI" title="Bollard Buddy AR - 2024 DreamXR Hackathon Demo" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media;picture-in-picture; web-share"></iframe>
<p>The app is simple:</p>
<ul>
<li>Press PLAY to start the AR view after scanning a QR code*</li>
<li>Then tap to place cones or other objects at the yellow cursor.</li>
<li>Choose between a few different traffic safety device models from the 3DStreet model library</li>
</ul>
<p>While cool, it is technically "table stakes" within the scope of AR app demos. But what's next makes it more useful.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="geospatial-qr-hack-for-fake-vps">Geospatial QR hack for fake VPS<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#geospatial-qr-hack-for-fake-vps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Geospatial QR hack for fake VPS" title="Direct link to Geospatial QR hack for fake VPS">​</a></h3>
<p>What makes BOLLARD BUDDY AR app unique compared to other AR "tap to place" demos is the connection to a specific location -- a longitude and latitude is embedded in the app QR code so that any objects placed in the scene can be localized relative to that longitude and latitude origin point.</p>
<p>This is extremely effective as a cheap and easy way to have a perfect "virtual positioning system" (or VPS) as long as the person posting the sign is capable of posting the sign at the very specific longitude and latitude (and orientation) associated with the QR code. This is easier than it sounds -- by simply dropping a pin on Apple or Google Maps at a clearly identifiable landmark such as a parking meter or telephone pole at a sufficient zoom level you can get a very precise longitude and latitude.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="create-and-share-from-mobile----serverless-with-no-auth">Create and share from mobile -- serverless with no auth<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#create-and-share-from-mobile----serverless-with-no-auth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Create and share from mobile -- serverless with no auth" title="Direct link to Create and share from mobile -- serverless with no auth">​</a></h3>
<p>The other unique BOLLARD BUDDY AR feature is sharing your newly created augmented reality street scene with other users (and even yourself) to refer to in the future.</p>
<p>Outside in the bright sun on the hot tarmac we don't want to challenge users with authentication or collecting data that requires keyboard input. How can we allow people to share a complicated geospatial scene without a server or authentication?</p>
<p>Our trick was to stuff the newly created scene data in the URL as url-encoded data. More specifically, a JSON representation of the array of 3D A-Frame entities and for each their mixin, position, rotation properties are all <a href="https://github.com/KilledByAPixel/JSONCrush" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">crushed</a> and placed as a querystring value in a new "Share URL".</p>
<p>Then we use the native OS share dialog to allow the user to choose how they want to share this, from copy/paste to sending message, email, AirDrop (my favorite) or more.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="challenges-with-web-based-augmented-reality">Challenges with web-based Augmented Reality<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#challenges-with-web-based-augmented-reality" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Challenges with web-based Augmented Reality" title="Direct link to Challenges with web-based Augmented Reality">​</a></h3>
<p>I've always been excited about the fun factor of AR and VR headsets, but recent technology advances in everyday smart phones means that the same tech is possible without a headset leveraging built-in AR libraries such as ARKit and ARCore on Apple and Android devices respectively.</p>
<p>The magic of these AR libraries is precision -- they have extremely accurate <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simultaneous_localization_and_mapping" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">simultaneous localization and mapping (SLAM)</a> available out-of-the-box for native apps usable on almost any device you may have in your pocket.</p>
<p>Until now these libraries have only been available for native applications, but recently web JavaScript-based access was made available on Android through WebXR AR Mode bindings. iOS devices using Safari have not yet supported WebXR AR Mode, however recently there have been a few "polyfill" workarounds. We are using <a href="https://launch.variant3d.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Variant Launch</a> which provides a (nearly) seamless experience for iOS users to instantly launch web-based AR apps. Behind the scenes, Variant Launch uses Apple's iOS "App Clips" feature to the underlying ARKit library through the WebXR JavaScript standard without needing to download an app first.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reaction-and-productization-1">Reaction and productization<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#reaction-and-productization-1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Reaction and productization" title="Direct link to Reaction and productization">​</a></h3>
<p>People often show surprise when using the app for the first time -- perhaps from the fun of reconfiguring public space for the first time, or the magic of discovering a super power they didn't realize their smart phone supported.</p>
<p>Some users see past the initial "Wow Moment" to practical use cases, especially for professional field measurement and planning for traffic control device placement or other civil engineering-related purpose. In fact, once users start placing basic cones provided in the default application it's not long before they start thinking of other objects they'd like to place and additional use cases.</p>
<p>We've continued development of this app concept, most recently adding new objects and improving usability and trying it out with real users at a street fair in San Francisco Saturday March 23.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/treat-fair-bollard-buddy-signage-960x0-877276f37f74e65e5f7a2a898de69fee.webp" width="960" height="640" class="img_ev3q">
<strong>Picture of a street fair with QR code on signage to collect feedback from community members using a modified version of BOLLARD BUDDY AR with plants, flowers and other street greening objects. <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/bayarea/article/treat-avenue-green-space-19362364.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Credit Benjamin Fanjoy/The Chronicle</a></strong></p>
<p>Similar to other geospatial features, there are fees incurred to make AR placement apps available across all devices (especially including iOS).</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="feedback-and-next-steps">Feedback and next steps<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/03/25/dev-blog-geospatial-and-augmented-reality-feature-research#feedback-and-next-steps" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Feedback and next steps" title="Direct link to Feedback and next steps">​</a></h2>
<p>I'd love to hear your feedback on this work at <a href="mailto:kieran@3dstreet.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">kieran@3dstreet.org</a>. Would you like these features? What is a price that you would pay for a subscription plan that includes these features?</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>webxr</category>
            <category>3dtiles</category>
            <category>google maps</category>
            <category>geospatial</category>
            <category>ar</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Creating Augmented Reality Street Scenes with Streetmix, 3DStreet and Adobe Aero]]></title>
            <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero</link>
            <guid>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[End-to-end street design to augmented reality (AR) visualization workflow.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/sZPPzIEDdoKCLolneDd8-145.05-2b18a10c24f8055f5cf44db93afee86e.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Greetings! I'm Marc Schlossberg, and I've been working alongside <a href="https://journalism.uoregon.edu/directory/faculty-and-staff/all/pimend" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Danny Pimentel</a> and graduate student <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/luke-walker-439b78119/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Luke Walker</a> at the University of Oregon on an exciting project: crafting augmented reality (AR) landscapes for our streets. What I have here is a practical, step-by-step guide designed to walk you through how to bring this innovative vision to your own neighborhood. So, let's roll up our sleeves and get our hands digitally dirty!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="getting-started-measuring-and-designing">Getting Started: Measuring and Designing<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero#getting-started-measuring-and-designing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Getting Started: Measuring and Designing" title="Direct link to Getting Started: Measuring and Designing">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/lVthCNUM7YLUyBGXixqk-10.87-80c85fce3c339171a8196f2efa2d7431.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q"><strong>First things first—measure up!</strong></p>
<p>To kick things off, you need to know how wide your street is. This is more straightforward than it sounds: just pop over to Google Street View or use an aerial photo, and get an approximate measurement. It's okay if it's not pinpoint accurate — we just need a ballpark figure.</p>
<p><strong>Crafting Your Street: Easy as Pie with Streetmix</strong></p>
<p>Once you've got your measurements, it's time to jump onto Streetmix—a free, user-friendly online tool that lets you reimagine that street space to your heart's content. Want to add bike lanes, benches, or green spaces? Simply drag and drop the elements you want to include, adjusting the widths to fit your street’s dimensions. Here’s where your creativity shines!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/J7eHGPI8MA57Pyzgsd8i-41.61-d8f2c4d7d54a990318659f4ac3f4bdbc.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q">For my project, I took a standard residential street and turned it into a car-free park, a delightful haven for community gatherings. Imagine that — but on your block! Feel free to start with the street I made - Demo St.: <a href="https://streetmix.net/schlossb/20/demo-st" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://streetmix.net/schlossb/20/demo-st</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="viewing-your-creation-3dstreets-magic">Viewing Your Creation: 3DStreet's Magic<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero#viewing-your-creation-3dstreets-magic" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Viewing Your Creation: 3DStreet's Magic" title="Direct link to Viewing Your Creation: 3DStreet's Magic">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/29P0QTWEp8JbvCQ8PeH3-63.32-928dbe2dd89a827b1be96ce08a2405c4.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>With your design all set in Streetmix, it's time to give it a touch of 3D flair. 3DStreet is a fantastic plugin that lets you visualize your newly designed street in all its three-dimensional glory. Explore your virtual environment, tweak and tune each element until you’re satisfied. It's a mini-adventure in urban planning from the comfort of your screen! You can go straight to my Demo St. in 3DStreet as well: <a href="https://3dstreet.app/#https://streetmix.net/schlossb/20/demo-st" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://3dstreet.app/#https://streetmix.net/schlossb/20/demo-st</a></p>
<p><strong>Trimming the Excess for AR</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/IkXMBseXhrpqImEJSANN-73.23-6ef8699ad042fd310f99859136492bb0.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>To prep for AR, you'll want to peel away the layers that aren’t needed—like buildings, to keep things neat. After simplifying, you can then export your model directly into a format that's ready for the world of augmented reality.</p>
<p>To delete a layer, select the layer in the left-hand panel -- such as "Buildings &amp; Blocks Container" in the screenshot above -- then press the <code>delete</code> key and click <code>ok</code>. This will remove buildings and grounds from lots that are not needed for our AR project.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="optional-tweaks-a-blender-bonus">Optional Tweaks: A Blender Bonus<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero#optional-tweaks-a-blender-bonus" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Optional Tweaks: A Blender Bonus" title="Direct link to Optional Tweaks: A Blender Bonus">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/kmXnEg7FMoHUxW0GgLiu-95.91-578b25b18098f554dd052bb2c580bdaa.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q">For the enthusiasts out there who relish fine-tuning, the free software Blender is your playground. Here, you can manipulate your 3D model to perfection. However, remember this is purely optional—the process is meant to be quick and streamlined.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bringing-it-to-life-augmented-reality-integration">Bringing It to Life: Augmented Reality Integration<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero#bringing-it-to-life-augmented-reality-integration" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bringing It to Life: Augmented Reality Integration" title="Direct link to Bringing It to Life: Augmented Reality Integration">​</a></h2>
<p>Alright, now to the magical part—transferring your 3D model to an augmented reality software. I personally use <a href="https://www.adobe.com/products/aero.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Adobe Aero</a>, thanks to the site license at the university, but there are other AR apps you can explore. This step allows you to add animations and make your scene come alive, although again, this step is not necessary for the "quick and dirty" path.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/tSVcvVL1kH92J4F4ALF8-112.94-b8f411524c96f6c05320da8bb061eba1.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>AR software opens with an empty workspace and, at least in Aero, you can simply drag and drop your 3D file onto the workspace and the whole thing magically appears. In many ways it will look exactly like it did in 3DStreet.</p>
<p><strong>Geolocation: Pinning It to the Real World</strong></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/M5vycvy2ClFbSLnLm6FY-133.23-1df718f2655ad0733ab2392a4b55bf57.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q">What’s truly remarkable with software like Adobe Aero is the ability to anchor your AR scene to a precise location on Earth. While this grounds your creation to a specific spot, it's not mandatory; you can always opt to apply your scene freely to any street you wish.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/sZPPzIEDdoKCLolneDd8-145.05-2b18a10c24f8055f5cf44db93afee86e.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="sharing-your-vision-universal-access">Sharing Your Vision: Universal Access<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero#sharing-your-vision-universal-access" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Sharing Your Vision: Universal Access" title="Direct link to Sharing Your Vision: Universal Access">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/KffxVJZ1prku9AeBBemu-158.27-35b296c693dca9c18355a51cd4cec663.png" width="640" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Once your AR scene is polished and ready, you create a shareable link through Adobe Aero. Anyone with this link can open it on their mobile device, head to the designated street, and behold—your digital transformation materializes before their eyes.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Your street is transformed into your scene that you can actually walk through and see what it would look like on your street, and you can go forward, backward, see all the different things that you've done, and really start to reimagine, well, what would this street look like if it wasn't a street as has been, but is actually a park, a place for people in this particular example?"</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/XP1Nfq1sugGz8zrILMJb-179.54-ef26283fc536ad6544d4f738185a220f.png" width="164" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/0ek0kL6ZzdbicjxigM67-181.43-22c585226e335ee1b14b58e95f808d17.png" width="167" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>To illustrate, envision wandering through the park that was once just a plain street—all through the magic of AR. Moving forward or backward, the entire scene is interactive and truly a game-changer for community engagement and urban design.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="wrapping-it-up">Wrapping It Up<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/30/creating-augmented-reality-ar-scenes-with-streetmix-3dstreet-adobe-aero#wrapping-it-up" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Wrapping It Up" title="Direct link to Wrapping It Up">​</a></h2>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/SjGd11l5Keu216ORRZav-189.75-a07c9c70fba466aa3c58909d4c55a87b.png" width="165" height="360" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>And there you have it—a dynamic overview of transforming streets with AR using some clever tools and a pinch of imagination. Not so intimidating now, right? With mostly free resources and a little bit of time, you can be on your way to designing, exploring, and sharing augmented realities that could pave the way for how we perceive and utilize our shared spaces.</p>
<p>Until next time, happy designing and thanks for joining me on this digital adventure. Bye for now!</p>
<h1>Video version of this post</h1>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AP1CwWuD7uA?si=y2_qAYNtR9HpATAl" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"></iframe>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>webxr</category>
            <category>gltf</category>
            <category>adobe aero</category>
            <category>streetmix</category>
            <category>ar</category>
            <category>vps</category>
            <category>localization</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Partner Spotlight: Zade's Contributions to 3DStreet in 2023]]></title>
            <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/29/partner-spotlight-zade</link>
            <guid>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/29/partner-spotlight-zade</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A spotlight on the contributions to 3DStreet from the software development team at Zade.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>2023 marks a significant year for 3DStreet, made possible through our <a href="https://github.com/3DStreet/3dstreet/graphs/contributors" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">talented community of contributors</a> both volunteer and paid. <a href="https://zade.agency/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Zade Agency</a> fits in the latter category as a software development team for-hire based in Ukraine. Over the past year Zade emerged as a major boost to our development productivity and I wanted to share how their contributions have helped 3DStreet in a critical time for the organization.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-challenge-for-3dstreet">The Challenge for 3DStreet<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/29/partner-spotlight-zade#the-challenge-for-3dstreet" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Challenge for 3DStreet" title="Direct link to The Challenge for 3DStreet">​</a></h3>
<p>To meet our timeline for a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WnjtUW4J8uc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">public beta launch of 3DStreet Editor in 2023</a>, we faced several challenges. A primary concern was the gap in React expertise among our existing development team. While we are skilled in various aspects, existing React knowledge was crucial for implementing deep and rapid modifications to <a href="https://github.com/3DStreet/3dstreet-editor" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">3DStreet Editor</a> which is a heavily modified version of the <a href="https://github.com/aframevr/aframe-inspector" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A-Frame inspector</a>.</p>
<p>Additionally, as a <a href="https://www.3dstreet.org/docs/about-3dstreet/3dstreet-llc-entity" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">self-funded project</a> we have very real budgetary constraints making it imperative to optimize every resource.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="zades-solution-to-boost-react-development">Zade's Solution to Boost React Development<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/29/partner-spotlight-zade#zades-solution-to-boost-react-development" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Zade's Solution to Boost React Development" title="Direct link to Zade's Solution to Boost React Development">​</a></h3>
<p>We found Zade through a direct personal referral via our designer <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/daria-dombrovska-933902207/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Daria Dombrovska</a>. Zade immediately brought a wealth of React knowledge through their team of both senior and junior engineers, filling the crucial skill gap in our team.</p>
<p>As a self-trained software developer myself, I worked directly with a senior engineer at the beginning to confirm our architectural approaches and details of our tech stack. I also worked with our account manager to agree on the use of <a href="https://github.com/orgs/3DStreet/projects/5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub Projects, issues, and PRs</a> to manage our working relationship.</p>
<p>For day-to-day tasks I create <a href="https://github.com/3DStreet/3dstreet-editor/issues/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub issues</a> that are prioritized in <a href="https://github.com/orgs/3DStreet/projects/5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Projects</a> and tackled via a junior engineer who is mentored by the experienced staff. Even as a junior engineer, they have way more experience in React fundamentals than I do given my <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%22aframevr%22%20(from%3Akfarr)&amp;f=live" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">rather myopic focus on A-Frame and three.js development</a> over the past decade.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2023-highlight-launching-3dstreet-cloud">2023 Highlight: Launching 3DStreet Cloud<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/29/partner-spotlight-zade#2023-highlight-launching-3dstreet-cloud" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2023 Highlight: Launching 3DStreet Cloud" title="Direct link to 2023 Highlight: Launching 3DStreet Cloud">​</a></h3>
<p>One of the most notable achievements in 2023 was the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WnjtUW4J8uc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">launch of 3DStreet Cloud</a>, a React application using <a href="https://firebase.google.com/docs/firestore" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Firebase Firestore</a> on <a href="https://cloud.google.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google Cloud Platform</a>.</p>
<p>3DStreet Cloud is the foundation of the growth engine of the <a href="https://3dstreet.app/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">3DStreet Editor product</a> -- it is the system that allows our users to collaborate on safe street designs and fulfill our core mission.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="zade-empowering-startups-with-react-expertise">Zade: Empowering Startups with React Expertise<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/29/partner-spotlight-zade#zade-empowering-startups-with-react-expertise" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Zade: Empowering Startups with React Expertise" title="Direct link to Zade: Empowering Startups with React Expertise">​</a></h3>
<p>Now it's time for the pitch, because the Zade team deserves it!</p>
<p>Are you an early-stage startup founder needing flexible React development solutions? Zade specializes in helping launch new startups and accelerating growth for existing ones. Their unique ecosystem is tailor-made for product development in the startup world.</p>
<p><strong>Zade's Offerings:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://zade.agency/launchkit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>LaunchKit:</strong></a> A program designed to bring your vision to life within a month.</li>
<li><strong>Integrated Team:</strong> Seamlessly scale your startup with Zade's integrated design and development team.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Special Offer for 3DStreet Community:</strong>
While there's no such thing as a free lunch in contract development, Zade extends a special offer to the 3DStreet community. Mention 3DStreet to receive a 15% discount on your first month with Zade – a deal that might just be more valuable than a few gourmet lunches, depending on your project's scale.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="connect-with-zade">Connect with Zade<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2024/01/29/partner-spotlight-zade#connect-with-zade" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Connect with Zade" title="Direct link to Connect with Zade">​</a></h3>
<p>Interested in learning more? Reach out to Zade at <a href="mailto:ivan@zade.agency" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ivan@zade.agency</a>, or contact me directly for an introduction. Let's embark on a journey of innovation and growth together with Zade's expert team!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>react</category>
            <category>development</category>
            <category>partner</category>
            <category>devshop</category>
            <category>web</category>
            <category>developer</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Impact on WebXR Application Design from New Mixed Reality Headsets]]></title>
            <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr</link>
            <guid>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[What changes should WebXR developers consider to their application given new devices coming to market?]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I attended a "developer day" at a local electronics company down the road featuring their new mixed reality VR headset. I spent the entire day testing many different WebXR applications with a heavy focus on evaluating which user interaction elements will be relevant for developers.</p>
<p>Below are some notes intended for other 3DStreet code contributors to reference as we work on supporting new WebXR compatible devices.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="gaze-works-very-well-as-a-primary-user-input-mechanism">Gaze works very well as a primary user input mechanism<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr#gaze-works-very-well-as-a-primary-user-input-mechanism" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Gaze works very well as a primary user input mechanism" title="Direct link to Gaze works very well as a primary user input mechanism">​</a></h2>
<p>Gaze interaction <em>"just works"</em> for native applications in this headset, however it's a privacy nightmare as gaze movement can be use to fingerprint (identify) individuals for tracking purposes, so that information isn't even given to native application.</p>
<p>To enable gaze user interface while not exposing gaze to the application, apps need to provide "hot spots" or hints as to areas that can be hovered. <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2023/10279/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">There is a great video guide on how to adapt 2D DOM CSS website for gaze highlight interaction</a>, but there's no clear equivalent to this CSS hinting that can be done in the WebXR "3D DOM" or 3D space. The need has been recognized however, <a href="https://github.com/immersive-web/proposals/issues/86" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">there is a new ticket opened in the WebXR <code>immersive-web</code> GitHub repository that I recently added to.</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="hand-tracking-is-the-most-accessible-input-not-controllers">Hand tracking is the most accessible input, not controllers<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr#hand-tracking-is-the-most-accessible-input-not-controllers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Hand tracking is the most accessible input, not controllers" title="Direct link to Hand tracking is the most accessible input, not controllers">​</a></h2>
<p>Imagine a world where WebXR experiences are 100% hands-free, where a simple ray from the wrist and a pitch of the hand can activate functions. This is not just a possibility but now a necessity -- going forward, all WebXR experiences must be accessible via hands first.</p>
<p>We should now regard hand tracking as the "lowest common denominator" of user input for headset experiences. Controllers will still offer higher precision, off-camera movement tracking, more button trigger inputs, etc. but they are no longer the most accessible "default" option.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="launching-webxr-applications">Launching WebXR applications<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr#launching-webxr-applications" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Launching WebXR applications" title="Direct link to Launching WebXR applications">​</a></h2>
<p>Getting WebXR working on this device is cumbersome. WebXR must be activated by searching through multiple Safari flags (System Settings &gt; Apps &gt; Safari &gt; Blah blah blah). Then, on the web page itself a user must accept 2 separate approval popups when entering WebXR mode -- one for enabling immersive mode, the other for enabling hand tracking.</p>
<p>It may be possible to "pull" some advanced users into using WebXR on these devices with instruction on feature flag setting, but it will be impossible to use WebXR on this platform to "push" more people to your WebXR experience in its present form.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="space-immersion-and-passthrough-with-webxr">Space, Immersion and Passthrough with WebXR<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr#space-immersion-and-passthrough-with-webxr" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Space, Immersion and Passthrough with WebXR" title="Direct link to Space, Immersion and Passthrough with WebXR">​</a></h2>
<p>In WebXR mode on the device, a scene is rendered in <em>Full Space</em> meaning no other application windows are present, unlike native apps that can choose to run in <em>Shared Space</em> amongst other applications. An additional limitation is that the device does not currently support WebXR with <em>Passthrough</em> mode, therefore you cannot run WebAR apps that make use of external cameras.</p>
<p><em>Therefore only your WebXR scene will appear in <em>Full Space</em> immersion mode with no <em>Passthrough</em>.</em> This may be desirable for traditional VR applications but not as useful for next generation mixed reality applications.</p>
<p>An additional limitation is that WebXR Immersive mode is limited to a 1.5m radius from the user-specified origin, usually where the user was located when entering XR mode. Beyond this radius the immersive scene <em>Full Space</em> begins fading into <em>Passthrough</em> without the scene persisting. If a user continues moving away from the origin the will see a round Safari icon at the origin point, presumably indicating that the user has an open WebXR Safari session with an origin at that point.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="diorama-vs-full-room-scale">Diorama vs. Full Room Scale<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr#diorama-vs-full-room-scale" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Diorama vs. Full Room Scale" title="Direct link to Diorama vs. Full Room Scale">​</a></h2>
<p>The <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/visionos/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">visionOS developer documentation</a> is excellent and signals clear directions for the market.</p>
<p>The Diorama appears to be major application interface concept, <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/visionos/diorama" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">featured as a sample application</a> and a prime example of output from the new Reality Composer Pro authoring tool.</p>
<p>This is a useful concept to adopt with 3DStreet. With 3DStreet there are cases for both Diorama and Full Scale modes: some users may wish to view a scene in Full Scale life-size to get an accurate viewpoint of dimension, while other users may wish to shrink a scene down to a Diorama view to easily manipulate a large scene from a smaller workspace.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="combining-webxr-with-native-applications">Combining WebXR with native applications<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr#combining-webxr-with-native-applications" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Combining WebXR with native applications" title="Direct link to Combining WebXR with native applications">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Native applications can ask for rights such as <em>Passthrough</em> or <em>Shared Space</em> that are not currently accessible via Safari WebXR. It is definitely worth exploring the use of an embedded webkit-based webview in a visionOS application which may expand the ability for WebXR application to offer augmented reality experiences with a native-like experience.</li>
<li>Reality Composer Pro looks like a powerful tool for non-developers. It is worth exploring a pipeline of 3DStreet &gt; Reality Composer Pro &gt; App Publishing. Therefore it is likely worth exploring tools to convert glTF exporting to USDZ format, or directly exporting the three.js / A-Frame scene into USDZ format.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="summary">Summary<a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/29/new-mixed-reality-devices-impact-on-webxr#summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary" title="Direct link to Summary">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>WebXR appears to be purposefully limited on this device with a degraded user experience. Consider webview or another mechanism to adapt WebXR application into a native app.</li>
<li>Hand tracking is now a minimum requirement for WebXR apps, controllers are optional.</li>
<li>Gaze interface is very effective but needs standardization work to enable in WebXR mode.</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>webxr</category>
            <category>headset</category>
            <category>mixed-reality</category>
            <category>ar</category>
            <category>vr</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Creating novel 3D scenes by compositing Gaussian splats with A-Frame and three.js]]></title>
            <link>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/21/gaussian-splat-compositing-for-constructed-street-scenes</link>
            <guid>https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/21/gaussian-splat-compositing-for-constructed-street-scenes</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[We share research and progress on improving the visual appearance of compositing new scenes from multiple splats using depth buffer and selective splat discarding.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>3DStreet's mission is to empower anyone to visualize safer streets. A common request to support this mission is to bring in local real-life elements from your actual streets by scanning them into 3D objects. Until now, the best technology for doing this (photogrammetry to textured 3D polygons) resulted in huge file sizes, difficult to edit output files, and gooey visuals like melting trees or cars that you may see on Google Maps in 3D mode.</p>
<p>Enter Gaussian Splatting -- earlier this year a groundbreaking photogrammetry and visualization technique called gaussian splatting was released as part of a <a href="https://repo-sam.inria.fr/fungraph/3d-gaussian-splatting/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">research paper published at SIGGRAPH 2023</a>. I believe splatting to be <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HVv_IQKlafQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the best modern method</a></em> to allow everyday users like you and me to scan 3D objects with our phones and retain the fine detail of organic material especially <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lowscL9YIjM" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">plants</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hr7P8_z0PSk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">trees</a>, flowers and other natural elements -- all things we'd like to see more of in our streets!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Side by side picture of the same apple tree showing 3d mesh vs. gaussian splat photogrammetry techniques" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/3d-mesh-vs-splat-16d7a8d0df770ca631c2b903d3b62a3f.jpg" width="1000" height="405" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>This is still an R&amp;D project, not yet a supported built-in feature of 3DStreet. In this post we share research and progress on how we are improving the visual appearance of compositing new scenes from multiple splats using depth buffer and selective splat discarding in three.js and A-Frame, underlying 3D frameworks supporting 3DStreet.</p>
<h1>A splatting explosion!</h1>
<p>A slew of gaussian splat tools have come to market -- creation apps for 3D scanning with your phone (<a href="https://poly.cam/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Polycam</a> and <a href="https://lumalabs.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Luma</a>) and viewers for every platform and device imaginable (<a href="https://github.com/tomiwaAdey/awesome-gaussian-splatting?tab=readme-ov-file#rendering-and-visualisation-tools" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">too many to list</a>) and even <a href="https://playcanvas.com/super-splat" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">browser-based cropping and editing tools</a>.</p>
<p>However, much of the existing gaussian splat research and development focuses on scenes with just one single large splat.</p>
<p>With 3DStreet we're exploring something new -- constructing brand new street scenes from bits and pieces of existing 3D splats.</p>
<h1>The problem: multiple splats in three.js are Hard</h1>
<p>If we can draw one gaussian splat in our scene, why not more? Well it turns out it's Hard. Compositing wasn’t supported yet by the existing three.js / A-Frame splat viewing libraries so it resulted in things just not good enough for people to use as a product, like this fire hydrant and tree being occluded by a flower box further away.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Picture of error in splat ordering resulting in distant objects incorrectly occluding closer objects" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/splat-render-order-error-b7464f2e90d5d0dc4f2679db3e4052e6.jpg" width="592" height="338" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>To solve this problem, we collaborated with <a href="https://arthurmoug.in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Arthur Mougin, a WebXR and full stack developer</a> who was excited to tackle a new challenge. Here is his writeup on how we enabled proper splat sorting, concluded by some discussion on what is coming next.</p>
<h1>Use depth buffer with <code>depthWrite:true</code></h1>
<p>After analyzing the shader and rendering pipeline of threejs, we identified first that we needed to have proper scene-level occlusion.</p>
<p>At the scene level, Splats are just classic opaque objects with a unique drawing method. That’s great because we can take advantage of the depth buffer. It’s a grayscale image that shaders use to know if their pixel below or above something that was already painted. By default, splats did not write into it, causing strange artifacts when the draw order does not match the depth order. Same thing for recursive occlusion.</p>
<p>So, we <a href="https://github.com/3DStreet/aframe-gaussian-splatting/pull/1/commits/dfa56ea471749e4864bfdedfcdd9c7c4aac9a656" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">added the ability to write the rendered splats to the depth buffer</a> with <code>depthWrite:true</code>. Turning it on improved our occlusion issues drastically.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="partial-splat-compositing-progress-occlusion-with-artifacts" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/partial-splat-compositing-progress-occlusion-with-artifacts-4553061baecc737b7e9029329be883ef.jpg" width="863" height="525" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h1>Fixing border and edge blending issues</h1>
<p>Sometimes the border is not completely clean, we also wanted a way to improve it.</p>
<p>It was done this time in the fragment shader, where discarding cause the pixel not to be drawn. <a href="https://github.com/3DStreet/aframe-gaussian-splatting/pull/1/commits/00d11e42f41a2adea824008ad81283001192176a" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">We compare there for each blob’s pixel their opacity, and if it’s lower than our limit, it’s not rendered.</a></p>
<p>This limit, the discard filter, has no effect when set to 0, but help cleanup unnecessary blobs that could ruin a proper transition between two splats. As it applies to all splat’s blobs, turning it on will impact the splats quality.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="gaussian-splat-depth-write-true-false-comparison" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/gaussian-splat-depth-write-true-false-comparison-fa2440f90d576f4eba2e36feee1b5f98.jpg" width="1640" height="516" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Unfortunately there is a trade off between different methods. As you can see in this next example below. On the right is the test scene with the original A-Frame splatting component that does not respect occlusion. On the left uses depthWrite which properly sorts the occlusion of the tree, fire hydrant, and flower box, but also results in artifacts especially visible on the bottom of the flower box where it meets the sidewalk.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="splat-compare-discard-filter-0-and-0.2" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/splat-compare-discard-filter-0-and-0.2-f7b44cee1f4a98019c440e3dcf0acf88.jpg" width="1408" height="800" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Adjusting <code>discardFilter</code> gives you control to find the right value, however as you continue to increase the <code>discardFilter</code> value approaching 1 the splats start to develop holes in the substrate and appear to be further apart.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="splat-compare-discard-filter-0.1-and-0.3" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/splat-compare-discard-filter-0.1-and-0.3-62e5d345a053a2838d2752379ad95fcb.jpg" width="1408" height="800" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>A partially effective mitigation for the artifacts is to tightly crop your splats using a tool like <a href="https://playcanvas.com/super-splat" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SuperSplat from PlayCanvas</a>.</p>
<h1>Updating the <code>aframe-gaussian-splatting</code> repository</h1>
<p>In the past we have been contributing changes directly to the <a href="https://github.com/quadjr/aframe-gaussian-splatting" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">original A-Frame Gaussian Splat library by quadjr</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/quadjr/aframe-gaussian-splatting/pull/25" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Arthur has suggested a PR with these changes</a>, but we wanted to publish this piece before those are able to merged so we have forked this repo in the 3DStreet GitHub organization for now.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="github-httpsgithubcom3dstreetaframe-gaussian-splatting">GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/3dstreet/aframe-gaussian-splatting" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/3dstreet/aframe-gaussian-splatting</a><a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/21/gaussian-splat-compositing-for-constructed-street-scenes#github-httpsgithubcom3dstreetaframe-gaussian-splatting" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to github-httpsgithubcom3dstreetaframe-gaussian-splatting" title="Direct link to github-httpsgithubcom3dstreetaframe-gaussian-splatting">​</a></h4>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="demo-scene-move-around-with-wasd-keys-https3dstreetgithubiosplat-playgroundbasiccompositing-demohtml">Demo scene (move around with <code>WASD</code> keys): <a href="https://3dstreet.github.io/splat-playground/basic/compositing-demo.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://3dstreet.github.io/splat-playground/basic/compositing-demo.html</a><a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/21/gaussian-splat-compositing-for-constructed-street-scenes#demo-scene-move-around-with-wasd-keys-https3dstreetgithubiosplat-playgroundbasiccompositing-demohtml" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to demo-scene-move-around-with-wasd-keys-https3dstreetgithubiosplat-playgroundbasiccompositing-demohtml" title="Direct link to demo-scene-move-around-with-wasd-keys-https3dstreetgithubiosplat-playgroundbasiccompositing-demohtml">​</a></h4>
<h4 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="demo-scene-source-also-uses-cutout-entity-httpsgithubcom3dstreetsplat-playgroundblobmainbasiccompositing-demohtml">Demo scene source (also uses cutout entity): <a href="https://github.com/3DStreet/splat-playground/blob/main/basic/compositing-demo.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/3DStreet/splat-playground/blob/main/basic/compositing-demo.html</a><a href="https://3dstreet.org/blog/2023/12/21/gaussian-splat-compositing-for-constructed-street-scenes#demo-scene-source-also-uses-cutout-entity-httpsgithubcom3dstreetsplat-playgroundblobmainbasiccompositing-demohtml" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to demo-scene-source-also-uses-cutout-entity-httpsgithubcom3dstreetsplat-playgroundblobmainbasiccompositing-demohtml" title="Direct link to demo-scene-source-also-uses-cutout-entity-httpsgithubcom3dstreetsplat-playgroundblobmainbasiccompositing-demohtml">​</a></h4>
<h1>Combining rasterization methods to add splats to 3DStreet scenes</h1>
<p>Now that we have support in the library for splat compositing, it's time to test what these look like in 3DStreet scenes.</p>
<p>We created a sample scene that loads a 3DStreet street scene with manually placed splat entities placed around the scene in appropriate locations. This was a first attempt to see how well the splats might fit in to a scene and what changes we need to make to 3DStreet Editor to support managing these with a user interface.</p>
<p>This picture shows a side-by-side view of the splat and low-poly mesh counterparts for the hybrid sedan and bus stop.
<img loading="lazy" alt="3dstreet-splat-compositing-demo" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/3dstreet-splat-compositing-demo-956f0b9516a47b5f42ebd24dd61de4fd.jpg" width="960" height="517" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Since each of these splats are A-Frame entities, the 3DStreet Editor can provide a quick way to move them around and arrange a custom scene.
<img loading="lazy" alt="3dstreet-editor-changing-scene-compositing-gaussian-splat" src="https://3dstreet.org/assets/images/3dstreet-editor-changing-scene-compositing-gaussian-splat-9752b16f3f11e2079f946de51ceb9ad6.jpg" width="1194" height="828" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h1>Try it for yourself</h1>
<p>We've created a proof of concept demo showing splats that I have scanned around San Francisco, combined with polygon mesh models automatically created from 3DStreet.</p>
<p><strong>Example scene (move around with <code>WASD</code> keys): <a href="https://github.com/3DStreet/splat-playground/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/3DStreet/splat-playground/</a></strong></p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-warning admonition_xJq3 alert alert--warning"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 16 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M8.893 1.5c-.183-.31-.52-.5-.887-.5s-.703.19-.886.5L.138 13.499a.98.98 0 0 0 0 1.001c.193.31.53.501.886.501h13.964c.367 0 .704-.19.877-.5a1.03 1.03 0 0 0 .01-1.002L8.893 1.5zm.133 11.497H6.987v-2.003h2.039v2.003zm0-3.004H6.987V5.987h2.039v4.006z"></path></svg></span>warning</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>Gaussian Splats in 3DStreet is a research project. Sometimes you need to reload once or twice for the splats to look better. If you're really adventurous press ctl + alt + i to access Editor but saving these scenes won't work and it will probably break. Be careful using this for real projects.</p></div></div>
<p>Does it work in WebXR? Yes, barely -- it requires a powerful device to maintain frame rate. Quest headsets and older phones have a hard time rendering this at full framerate.</p>
<h1>What's next</h1>
<p>This is still a research technology. Even just in the past week there was a <a href="https://lumalabs.ai/luma-web-library" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">whole new WegGL splat viewing library released by Luma AI</a> and more research on this topic seems to drop every week. Likely the method that we've come up with will be replaced with a fancy new algorithm soon.</p>
<p>We'll keep iterating on the applications of this technology for street safety and more general urban design use cases. If this resonates with users we can explore how to make this accessible so that all users can create custom splat scenes with models they scan from their own streets.</p>
<p><a href="https://discord.gg/VN242sx9qu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Join our community to continue the conversation!</a></p>
<h1>Video version of this post</h1>
<iframe width="580" height="420" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fy8PefDy5VY?si=pJ7F6j_mmmA2yo31" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"></iframe>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>gaussian splats</category>
            <category>splats</category>
            <category>photogrammetry</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>